Finding Aid for Urban Options records, 1976-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Urban Options records
1976-2008
Urban Options (Organization)
2011007 Bn 2
Non-profit organization providing energy efficiency information and services to homes and businesses in Michigan. Name changed in 2009 to Michigan Energy Options. Collection includes administrative and financial files; records of grants, programs, and services; documentation of the Energy Demonstration House; records of the organization’s work with regional task forces and issue advocacy; seminar and curriculum development materials; printed brochures and newsletters; press releases and clippings; and photographs and slides of staff and volunteers, the Energy Demonstration House, and exhibits and events.
14.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Michigan Energy Options (donor no. 10439 ) in September, 2010.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Urban Options (as of 2009, known as Michigan Energy Options) is a non-profit community agency that provides energy and environmental information and services. Founded in 1978 in response to the energy crisis, Urban Options promotes awareness of energy efficiency measures, advocates for conservation efforts and sustainable energy policy, and provides services to increase energy efficiency in homes and businesses in Michigan. The organization's programs include residential and commercial energy audits, home weatherization, and energy-related curriculum development. Urban Options also maintains a library of books, videos, periodicals, and reference materials on a variety of environmental topics and conducts educational programs for children and adults on energy conservation, sustainable energy, composting, and ecological landscaping.
Urban Options operates an Energy and Environmental Demonstration House, located in East Lansing. The house was originally leased from the City of East Lansing in 1978 and was retrofitted by staff and volunteers through a series of workshops. In 1987, the house was moved from its original location at 135 Linden to its current location at 405 Grove Street to make room for a new parking lot for City Hall. Over the years, Urban Options and its volunteers have continued to make improvements to the house. The Energy Demonstration House uses energy efficient materials, structures, and appliances, and features exhibits on insulation, water conservation, air leakage, composting, ecological landscaping, solar energy, and recycling. A second Energy Demonstration Center, located in Marquette, is operated by the northern branch of Michigan Energy Options, formerly known as Northern Options.
The Urban Options records provide an in-depth look at the work of this non-profit energy efficiency organization from its founding in 1978 until 2002. The collection documents how Urban Options was managed as it grew and integrated new services; how programs were developed and implemented; how the organization delivered its message of energy efficiency and sustainability through publications and media outreach, and how it sought institutional and individual support for its work. The records are arranged into eight series.
Subjects:
Compost--Michigan.; Dwellings--Energy conservation--Michigan.; Energy conservation--Michigan--East Lansing.; Energy conservation--Study and teaching.; Energy policy--Michigan.; Recycling (Waste, etc.)--Michigan.; Solar energy--Michigan.; Urban Options (Organization)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Compost--Michigan.; Dwellings--Energy conservation--Michigan.; Solar energy--Michigan.; Urban Options (Organization)
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Slides (photographs); Videotapes.
- Administrative and Financial, 1978-2007
  The Administrative and Financial series documents the management of the organization, and includes board of directors' minutes, planning materials, financial statements, annual reports, procedure manuals, and correspondence. The bulk of the correspondence in this series consists of letters sent by Executive Director LeRoy Harvey and a smaller number sent by his successor Patrick Hudson. There are some incoming letters as well, but the majority of incoming correspondence is filed by the program or activity to which it pertains.
  - Annual reports, 1979-1990 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Articles of incorporation and non-profit filings, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - Awards, 1990-2002 (Box 1)
  - Board and staff notebook, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Board and staff update, 1996-2000 (Box 1)
  - Board correspondence, 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - Board development, 2001-2003 (Box 1)
  - Board handbook, 2002 (Box 1)
  - Board material, 1991-2003; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Board member manual, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Board minutes and planning, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - Board minutes, 1981-1997; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Board minutes, 1997-1998 (Box 2)
  - Board records, 1982-2004; 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Board/planning materials, 1990-2002; 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Board updates and minutes, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
  - Budget, 2001-2003 (Box 2)
  - Bylaws, 1997-2000 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1989-2002; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Financial reports, 1991-1992 (Box 3)
  - Financial statements and auditor's reports, 1989-2001; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Lease agreement, 1991-1992 (Box 3)
  - Staff: job descriptions, resumes, staff letters, 1997-1999 (Box 3)
  - Urban Options case statement, 1996-1997 (Box 3)
  - Urban Options duties and procedures, 1997-2003 (Box 3)
  - Urban Options history, circa 1989 (Box 3)
  - Urban Options handbook, circa 1991 (Box 3)
  - Urban Options manual, circa 1998 (Box 3)
  - Urban Options/Northern Options emergency response plan, 2007 (Box 3)
  - Urban Options notebook, circa 1979 (Box 3)
  - Urban Options volunteer orientation packet/trainer's manual, 1996-2001 (Box 3)
- Policy and Issue Advocacy, 1981-2002
  Policy and Issue Advocacy is a small series documenting Urban Options' work to increase public support and influence government policy on issues relating to sustainable energy. Subjects in this series include the Clean Energy Campaign and energy policy in East Lansing and Ingham County. Materials include policy statements, correspondence, press releases, and meeting notes and agendas.
  - Clean Energy Campaign, 1993-1994; 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Community Energy Plan for East Lansing proposal, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Energy policy, 2000-2002 (Box 3)
  - Energy policy, Ingham County and East Lansing, 1981-1990 (Box 3)
  - Residential Conservation Services legislation, 1983-1986 (Box 4)
  - Utilities/energy conservation reviews, 1991-1992 (Box 4)
- Regional Committees and Task Forces, 1979-2004
  The Regional Committees and Task Forces series contains records of collaborations among Michigan energy and environmental organizations to develop energy efficiency and sustainability programs for communities in the state. Committees represented in this series include the Tri-Country Regional Energy Consortium and Earth Share of Michigan. Materials include program proposals, reports, correspondence, and meeting notes and agendas. Records of work done primarily by Urban Options staff for some of these projects can also be found in the Programs and Services series.
  - Beaver Island project, 1991-1992 (Box 4)
  - Citizens Conservation Corporation (CCC) grant proposal, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Community Energy Management Program
    - Assorted materials, 1984-1985; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Neighborhood Open Houses, 1985 (Box 4)
      (includes photographs)
    - Saving Energy in East Lansing, 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - Earth Share of Michigan, 2001-2003 (Box 4)
  - East Lansing Community Based Economic Development workshop proposal, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Energy Advisory Board, 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - Energy Services Cooperative planning, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Great Lakes Energy Network, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Energy Demonstration Centers joint project, 2004 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Energy Education Network (MEENet), 2000-2003 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Roundtable on Energy/Environment, 1991-1992 (Box 4)
  - Tri-County Regional Energy Consortium, 1993-1998; 8 folders (Box 4)
  - Tri-County Regional Energy Consortium, 1993-1998; 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Red Cedar Watershed, 1999-2001 (Box 5)
  - Red Cedar River, fishing on campus ordinance, 2002 (Box 5)
  - Regional Recycling Coordinators Committee, 1992-1993 (Box 5)
  - Sustainable Community project planning, 2001-2002 (Box 5)
  - Urban Options Energy Consortium statement of qualifications, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Utilities Assistance Task Force, 1994-1995 (Box 5)
- Programs and Services, 1976-2007
  Records in the Programs and Services series document the organization's work providing energy efficiency services and demonstrating conservation methods and sustainable energy applications. This series is divided into three subseries. The largest of these, Program Files, contains program proposals, progress reports, correspondence, and meeting notes for programs offered by Urban Options, including audits of residential and commercial energy use, solar and wind energy demonstrations, composting and recycling, and green commuting options. This subseries also contains files documenting the history of the Energy Demonstration House. The Grants and Contracts subseries documents work done by Urban Options for Lansing, East Lansing, and Ingham County. The final subseries, Reference Files, contains miscellaneous reports and studies on solar energy and transportation, and information on a number of home energy audit services around the United States.
  - Program Files
    - Board of Water and Light, Energy Fitness visits, 1989-1991 (Box 5)
    - Community Energy Project
      - Affordable Housing Vendor Fair proposal, 2001 (Box 5)
      - Biodiesel Education Project, 2004-2007 (Box 5)
      - Fiber Optic Light Pipe, 2000-2001 (Box 5)
      - Green Commuting Project, 2002-2005; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Photovoltaic and Wind Generator Demonstration proposal, 1998 (Box 5)
      - Solar Car Demonstration, 2002-2003 (Box 5)
      - Solar Demonstration Project proposal, 2000 (Box 5)
      - Solar Energy Demonstration, Electric Vehicle Charging Station, 2003 (Box 5)
      - Solar Food Cart proposal, 2001 (Box 5)
      - Solar Home Tour, 2001-2005 (Box 5)
      - Wind Energy Project proposal, 2001 (Box 5)
        (submitted by Growing In Place; Urban Options consulted on the proposal)
    - Composting and Backyard Recycling, 1991-1995 (Box 5)
    - Compost Education, 1999-2003 (Box 5)
    - Consumers Power Company, Energy Services, 1990-1993 (Box 5)
    - Demonstration House
      - Addition plans and comments, 1991-1994 (Box 6)
      - Assorted materials, 1978-1999; 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Certificates, permits, and variances, 1991-1993 (Box 6)
      - Communications with City of East Lansing, 1978 (Box 6)
      - Drawings and Polaroid photos, undated (Box 6)
      - Exhibit proposal and Exhibit Committee notes, 1991-1996 (Box 6)
      - Expenses, 1992-1994 (Box 6)
      - History, 1978-1994; 2 folders (Box 6)
        (second folder includes photographs)
      - House Committee minutes, 1989-1990 (Box 6)
      - House fire, 2002 (Box 6)
      - Information packet, 1988 (Box 6)
      - Progress reports, 1978-1979 (Box 6)
      - Renovations, 1989-1992; 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Report by Sarah Whitford, 1993 (Box 6)
      - Site plan, 1988 (Box 6)
      - Solar roof, 2000-2002 (Box 6)
        (includes photographs; see Audiovisual series for additional photos of solar roof)
      - Space sharing joint operating agreement, 1989-1991 (Box 6)
      - Tour information, 1993-2004 (Box 6)
      - Tours and open houses, 1982; undated (Box 6)
    - Energy Demonstration Center Project, 2001-2002; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Energy Education Integration Project proposal, 2003 (Box 7)
    - Energy Efficiency Home Partnership Project, 2001-2003 (Box 7)
      (Great Lakes Housing Coalition and Urban Options joint project)
    - Energy Efficient Homes seminars, 2000-2003 (Box 7)
    - Energy Efficient Marketing Project reports, 1998-1999 (Box 7)
    - Energy Fitness, 1988-2006; 12 folders (Box 7)
    - Energy Star, 1999-2005; 5 folders (Box 7)
    - Energy Wise, 2005-2006 (Box 8)
    - Enterprise Community Program, Housing, 1994 (Box 8)
    - Five Star Energy Grant Program, 2000-2002 (Box 8)
    - Go Green Program, 1997-1999; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Great Lakes Energy Efficient Motor Rally (GLEEM) Project, 2003 (Box 8)
    - Hands On Energy Activities for Teachers (HEAT) Project, 1993-1995; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Home *A*Syst, 1997-2000 (Box 8)
    - Home *A*Syst and The Landscape Consultation (TLC), 2000 (Box 8)
    - Home Energy Check Up Service, 2001 (Box 8)
    - Local Bicycle Use Promotion proposal, 1980 (Box 8)
    - Low Income Energy Efficiency grants, 2001-2003 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Business for Energy Efficiency (MBEE), 1997-2001; 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Michigan Energy Centers Network (MECNet), 1999-2003; 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Michigan Energy Centers Network (MECNet), 1999-2001; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous program proposals, 1994-2001; 4 folders (Box 9)
    - Quality of Life Bond Program: Resource Recovery Education proposal, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Solar Action Program, 1980-1981 (Box 9)
    - Solar Greenhouse Demonstration Project, 1978-1980; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Solar Greenhouse Monitoring and Education Project, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Solar Hot Water Rebate Program, 2005 (Box 9)
    - Sustainable Community Dialogue Project, 2001 (Box 9)
    - Task Force for Appropriate Technology proposal, 1978 (Box 9)
    - Transportation Task Force report, 1979 (Box 9)
    - Waste and Waste Water Management Task Force report, 1979 (Box 9)
  - Grants and Contracts
    - City of Lansing and City of East Lansing contracts, 1992-1996; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - City of East Lansing proposals for services, 1994-1995 (Box 9)
    - Community Development Block Grant
      - Assorted materials, 1996-1997 (Box 10)
      - Grant notebook, 1981-1984 (Box 10)
      - Lansing Energy Fitness, 1992-2005 (Box 10)
      - Lansing housing studies, 1991-1996; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Grant contracts, 1991-1996; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Ingham County contracts, 2000-2003 (Box 10)
  - Reference Files
    - Atlas of Community Resources, 1978 (Box 10)
    - Home Energy Audit programs, 1979-1995; 5 folders (Box 10)
    - Lansing Community College Solar Applications course materials, 1979 (Box 10)
    - Lansing Housing Commission Energy Audit, undated (Box 10)
    - Michigan Solar Energy resources, 1978-1979 (Box 10)
    - Planning for Energy Conservation draft report, 1976 (Box 10)
    - Transportation reports, 1977-1980 (Box 10)
- Education, 1980-2006
  The Education series contains two subseries. Seminars and Curriculum Development includes records of workshops and seminars given by the organization on composting, ecological landscaping, solar energy, and bicycle commuting; and materials and curriculum ideas for teaching energy related topics. Additional curriculum development records can be found in the Programs and Services series. The Subject Files subseries of Education contains an assortment of information on topics such as composting, native plants, tree planting, hazardous household waste, and organic pest control.
  - Seminars and Curriculum Development
    - Backyard Habitat Project, 1995-1996 (Box 11)
    - Bicycle commuting seminar, 2002 (Box 11)
    - Community Energy Management: Community Energy Education Project, 1986-1987 (Box 11)
    - Compost education program, 1995-2006; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Compost lecture service, 2001 (Box 11)
    - Compost workshops and related materials, 1982-1993 (Box 11)
    - Education committee notes and correspondence, 2001-2002 (Box 11)
    - Education, miscellaneous materials, 1996-1999 (Box 11)
    - Education programs, 1983; 1990-1992 (Box 11)
    - Educator survey, 1990-1991 (Box 11)
    - Field trip guide, 1995 (Box 11)
    - Future Friendly Homes Project, 1996 (Box 11)
    - Project Energy for Conservation District Trainers, 2002 (Box 11)
    - Renewable Energy Curriculum Project, 1997-1999 (Box 11)
    - Service Learning Center Writing Project, 2000 (Box 11)
    - Smart Landscaping seminar, 1997-1999 (Box 11)
    - Solar Hot Water Heater seminar, 1980 (Box 11)
    - Solar/Wind Electricity workshop, 1999 (Box 11)
    - Sustainability and Energy Education Project, 1993-2000 (Box 11)
    - The Landscape Consultation (TLC) materials, 1997; undated (Box 11)
    - Tollgate Wetlands Project, 1993-1999 (Box 11)
    - Waste Information Series for Educators (WISE) curriculum, 1996-1997 (Box 11)
    - Williamston adult enrichment classes, 2001 (Box 11)
  - Subject Files
    - Community and urban gardening, 1995-1998 (Box 11)
    - Composting, 1992-2000 (Box 11)
    - Conservation organizations, 1996-2001 (Box 12)
    - Forestry/tree planting, 1993-1999 (Box 12)
    - Greening of Detroit, 2001 (Box 12)
    - Hazardous household waste, 1992; undated (Box 12)
    - Native plants, 1999-2000 (Box 12)
    - Organic pest control, undated (Box 12)
    - Rainwater collection, undated (Box 12)
    - Sustainability, 1995-1998 (Box 12)
    - Sustainable living, 1995-2000 (Box 12)
- Fundraising and Events, 1980-2008
  Fundraising and Events is another small series. It includes documentation of Urban Options' planning for fundraising campaigns and donor appeals, as well as the organization's participation in energy fairs, Earth Day celebrations, and other public events.
  - Calendars of events, 1980-2001 (Box 12)
  - Earth Day, 1996-2008 (Box 12)
  - Energy fairs, 1991-2000 (Box 12)
  - Events, 1991-2006; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Fundraising, 1989-1990; 6 folders (Box 12)
  - Greater Lansing Foundation funding requests, 1987-1990 (Box 12)
  - Solar Home Tour, 1998-2003 (Box 12)
- Communications, 1979-2005
  The Communications series contains two subseries. Publications and Information Resources includes materials produced by Urban Options, such as newsletters, brochures, and fact sheets, and information about the organization's library and website. The Publicity subseries contains press releases and newspaper clippings about Urban Options and energy efficiency issues.
  - Publications and Information Resources
    - Brochures, guides, and flyers, 1979-1998; undated; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Brochures and guides, other organizations, 1996-1998; undated (Box 13)
    - Energy Fitness presentation, 1991 (Box 13)
    - Fact Sheets and Energy Fitness Tips, 1985-1993; undated (Box 13)
    - Library resources and notes, 1998; undated (Box 13)
    - Sundial newsletter, 1984-2003; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Urban Options presentation and transparencies, undated (Box 13)
    - Video production notes, 1990-1997 (Box 13)
    - Website development, 1996-1997 (Box 13)
  - Publicity
    - Clippings, 1978-2005; 8 folders (Box 13)
    - Clippings and published materials, 1978-1990 (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous publicity materials, 1989-2000 (Box 14)
    - Press releases, 1998-2005 (Box 14)
- Audiovisual, 1979-1996; undated
  The final series, Audiovisual, includes photographs and slides documenting the organization, its staff and volunteers, the Energy Demonstration house, displays and exhibits, seminars and demonstrations, and meetings and events attended by Urban Options members. This series also includes two motion picture films about energy in Michigan, and a sample of thermograms (thermal images of infrared radiation) taken of residences, business, and public buildings in East Lansing as part of the Saving Energy in East Lansing program. In addition to the thermograms, there is an interpretation guide, a brief video produced by Urban Options promoting the program, and several slides and small photographic prints of thermal images.
  - Photographs
    - Demonstration House, 2 envelopes; 1 folders (Box 14)
    - Demonstration House renovation, exterior, 2 envelopes (Box 14)
    - Demonstration House renovation, interior, 2 envelopes (Box 14)
    - Exhibits and displays, 2 envelopes (Box 14)
    - Landscaping and composting (Box 14)
    - Lead Safe Community (Box 14)
    - Meetings and events (Box 14)
    - Meetings and miscellaneous photographs (Box 14)
    - Michigan Business for Energy Efficiency (MBEE) (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 14)
    - Solar Greenhouse, 1 envelopes; 1 folders (Box 14)
    - Solar panels and greenhouses (Box 14)
      (includes images of homes in Haslett and Perry, MI)
    - Solar roof installation (Box 14)
    - Staff and volunteers, 2 envelopes (Box 14)
    - Urban Options picnic (Box 14)
  - Slides
    - Demonstration House and miscellaneous slides, 1982-1994 (Box 14)
    - Energy Fitness, 1988 (Box 14)
    - From Yard Waste to Yard Riches workshop, 1991-1992 (Box 14)
    - Grass demonstration and composting, 1992; 1994 (Box 14)
    - Urban Options presentation, 1979-1996 (Box 14)
  - Thermograms
    - Rolled thermogram photographs, circa 1985 (Box 15)
      (10 rolled photographs)
    - Thermogram interpretation guide and related materials, undated (Box 15)
    - Photographs and slides, 1982-1987 (Box 15)
    - Thermogram video, 1986 (Box 15)
      (VHS video, approximately 5 minutes, introducing the thermogram program)
  - Motion pictures
    - "Energy Ann Arbor,", undated; 7 in. film reel (Box 15)
    - "Solar Energy: It's Working in Michigan,", undated; 7 in. film reel (Box 15)